CRAIG P. HUTTON

I am a data scientist and lead investigator with the Province of British Columbia's Data Innovation Program. My diverse training in applied statistics, behavioural neuroscience, and epidemiology leads me to apply a multidisciplinary and creative approach to doing research. I deeply enjoy solving complex problems and exploring new ideas.

EXPERIENCE

2021 Present

Data Science Consultant

Winstanley Laboratory, University of British Columbia ♥ Vancouver, BC

· Computational modelling of decision-making which revealed impacts of Cannabis on impulsivity.

2020 Present

Data Scientist

Government of British Columbia

- · Statistical modelling, hypothesis testing, causal inference, and machine learning with R.
- Population-level predictive modelling and analysis of educational attainment, homelessness, housing instability, poverty, and drug overdose risk.
- Research findings led to \$633 million in funding for homelessness • Leading a team of 3 in designing in BC: https://news.gov.bc.ca /releases/2022AG0012-000369
- · Service demand forecasting using time-series analysis and regression modelling in R.

♥ Victoria, BC

- · Advising executives and stakeholders on research methods to address strategic knowledge gaps.
- · Querying, modifying, and constructing relational databases using SQL and SAS.
- · Recruiting, training, and supervising research staff.
- and conducting randomized controlled trials of behavioural insights interventions to improve employment outcomes for income assistance clients in BC.

2019-2020

Data Science Fellow

Government of British Columbia

- Evaluated the economic impacts of Queried and modified relational financial assistance policies with time-series regression models.
- · Created an R package to facilitate exploratory data analysis: bcgov.github.io/elucidate/

♥ Victoria. BC

Victoria. BC

- databases using SQL.
- · Constructed high throughput data processing pipelines to facilitate rapid and reproducible analysis.

2018-2019

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Division of Medical Sciences, University of Victoria

- · Employed a decision tree in R to
- predict the concussion status of 457 patients with 95% accuracy.
- · Used clustering to identify disease patterns across Canada, the United States, England, and Ireland

CONTACT INFO

- □ craig.hutton@gmail.com
- github.com/huttoncp
- twitter.com/huttoncp
- in linkedin.com/in/huttoncp/
- craig.rbind.io
- ncraig.rbind.io/post/
- **J** +1 250-884-1550

For more information, please contact me via email.

SKILLS

Scientific Research Applied Statistics Machine Learning **Project Management** Leadership Teaching **Public Speaking** Software Development Microsoft Office

DATA ANALYSIS

Data Visualisation (e.g. ggplot2) Linear Models (GLM, GLMM) Additive Models (GAM, GAMM) Time-Series Forecasting CART, Random Forests, XGBoost PCA. MCA. Factor Analysis. FAMD Cluster Analysis (e.g. k-means) Deep Learning (MLP, RNN, CNN) Bayesian Analysis (e.g. brms) Causal Inference (DAGs) Missing Data Imputation (mice)

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Psychology 2018

2013

2022

Present

2021

McMaster University

Hamilton, ON

Awarded \$137,500 in competitive scholarships

Hons. B.Sc. in Biopsychology

University of Winnipeg

♥ Winnipeg, MB

• Awarded \$7,000 in competitive scholarships

RECENT TALKS

Socioeconomic, demographic, and health predictors of drug 2022 overdose in the BC Provincial Overdose Cohort.

BC Centre for Disease Control Grand Rounds

♦ Vancouver, BC

• ■ https://craig.rbind.io/talks/bccdc2022

Socioeconomic, demographic, and health predictors of drug overdose in the BC Provincial Overdose Cohort.

Employment and Social Development Canada

Victoria. BC

Social assistance and health in Vancouver's Downtown 2020 Eastside neighbourhood

BC Government Deputy Ministers Board on Integrated Data

♥ Victoria, BC

COMMUNITY ROLES

Data Expert in Residence 2021-

Innovation Hub; BC Public Service

♥ Victoria, BC

Blog Editor & Content Creator 2019-Present

Data Science Studio; University of Victoria

♥ Victoria, BC

TECHNICAL PAPERS

2022 Socioeconomic, health, and demographic predictors of drug overdose in British Columbia from 2015-2018.

Government of British Columbia

♥ Victoria, BC

Socioeconomic, health, and academic predictors of high 2022 school graduation in Vancouver from 2000-2009.

Government of British Columbia ♥ Victoria, BC

Social Assistance and Health in Vancouver's Downtown Eastside Neighbourhood from 1995-2017.

Government of British Columbia ♥ Victoria, BC

9 scientific papers, 148 citations, h-index = 6

craig.rbind.io/scholar

PROGRAMMING

R / tidyverse / data.table SQL / MySQL SAS / SPSS Python / keras h2o / Spark Parallel Processing git / GitHub / GitLab Bash

REPRODUCIBLE REPORTING

R Markdown blogdown Jupiter Notebooks flexdashboards

T CERTIFICATES

Behavioural Insights

University of British Columbia Vancouver, BC | 2022-2023 (expected)

Future Leaders Program

Government of British Columbia Victoria, BC | 2021-2022

Fundamentals of OCAP®

First Nations Information Governance Centre Ottawa, ON | 2021

> This resume was built with the pagedown R package.